<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo on Tom&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://gagor.pl/tags/hugo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hugo on Tom&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Content licensed under &lt;a rel=&#34;license noopener noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;(CC BY-SA 4.0)&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://gagor.pl/tags/hugo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Hugo static site redirects with Cloudflare Pages</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pl/2024/03/optimizing-hugo-static-site-redirects-with-cloudflare-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pl/2024/03/optimizing-hugo-static-site-redirects-with-cloudflare-pages/</guid>
      <description>I used to utilize GitHub Pages to serve static content for my blog. I secured it behind Cloudflare to employ a custom domain and automate HTTPS certificate management. Additionally, I utilized a few Page Rules to implement redirects:
From www.* to non-www, From HTTP to HTTPS, And for some SEO renaming. Unfortunately, in the Free plan from Cloudflare, you are limited to:
3 Page Rules (with simple glob matching), 10 Transformation Rules (no regex rules), 10 Redirect Rules (no regex).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adding Mermaid diagrams to Hugo</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pl/2024/02/adding-mermaid-diagrams-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pl/2024/02/adding-mermaid-diagrams-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>I used Chart.js charts on one of my Hugo blogs for few years already. Recently I needed to add few diagrams and I started glueing them in Chart.js but then I found that Hugo supports GoAT and Mermaid diagrams&amp;thinsp; external link . They&amp;rsquo;re not working out of the box, but it&amp;rsquo;s easy to extend. Much easier than my custom shortcodes.
I tried to follow up the instruction1 but failed. After few minutes I found slightly simpler solution.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Changing comments provider for my blog</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pl/2023/12/changing-comments-provider-for-my-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pl/2023/12/changing-comments-provider-for-my-blog/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about switching comments system to something different on my blog. Since I moved to Hugo&amp;thinsp; external link , I used Disqus&amp;thinsp; external link . Integration was easy and it was also easy to move comments from Wordpress. Maybe the move was easy, but people somehow didn&amp;rsquo;t like the interface. I receive 6 comments since I switched from Wordpress 3 years ago &amp;#x1f604; To be honest, I don&amp;rsquo;t like it too.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bye Bye Wordpress!</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pl/2020/10/bye-bye-wordpress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pl/2020/10/bye-bye-wordpress/</guid>
      <description>I started my blog on custom (written by my) engine, but as I didn&amp;rsquo;t had enough time to enhance it I switched to Wordpress. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using Wordpress as an engine of my blog for past 8~9 years. I have small VPS with PHP + Nginx and you can find a lot of configuration examples from my config on this site &amp;#x1f604;
There was a time, when I was really satisfied by what it provides.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
