<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Docker on timor's site</title><link>https://timor.site/tags/docker/</link><description>Recent content in Docker on timor's site</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://timor.site/tags/docker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How old are Docker Official Images?</title><link>https://timor.site/2021/01/how-old-are-docker-official-images/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://timor.site/2021/01/how-old-are-docker-official-images/</guid><description>TL;DR
They&amp;rsquo;re old, some of them were not updated for months!
As a professional DevOps I concern about a lot of things&amp;hellip; but security is always close to the top of the list. With Docker build environments and deployments became much more stable, which often is a result of just being stale ;/
I&amp;rsquo;ve been talking about this for long time but it&amp;rsquo;s still hard for people to believe it.</description></item><item><title>Automatically build after file change</title><link>https://timor.site/2016/02/automatically-build-after-file-change/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://timor.site/2016/02/automatically-build-after-file-change/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m playing a lot with Docker lately. Building images, and then rebuilding, and then building again&amp;hellip; It&amp;rsquo;s pretty boring. To automate this task a little I used inotify to build automatically after I changed any file. This trick could be used in many different situations.
You will need inotify-tools package:
sudo apt-get install -y inotify-tools Then run something like this:
while inotifywait -e modify -r .; do docker-compose build; done This commands will rebuild my Docker images after any file change in current directory.</description></item><item><title>Install Docker Compose</title><link>https://timor.site/2016/02/install-docker-compose/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://timor.site/2016/02/install-docker-compose/</guid><description>When I started playing with Docker I was running a lot of commands to build image, delete containers running on old image, run containers based on new image, etc&amp;hellip; A lot of log commands with links, volumes, etc&amp;hellip;
Then I started searching for something to automate this task and here I get to docker-compse command, this is how you may install it:
pip install docker-compose And install additional bash completions (run as root):</description></item><item><title>Manual installation of Docker on Debian/Ubuntu</title><link>https://timor.site/2016/02/manual-installation-of-docker-on-debian-ubuntu/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://timor.site/2016/02/manual-installation-of-docker-on-debian-ubuntu/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve played with Docker a little in it early days but didn&amp;rsquo;t stick for longer with it. It&amp;rsquo;s stable now so I wanted to check how it&amp;rsquo;s running now.
I really can&amp;rsquo;t accept this method of installation:
curl -fsSL https://get.docker.com/ | sh I think that world is going to it&amp;rsquo;s end when I see such scritps&amp;hellip; I prefer to do this manually, knowing exactly what I have to do.
Install prerequisites:</description></item><item><title>Some usefull commands in Docker</title><link>https://timor.site/2016/02/some-usefull-commands-in-docker/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://timor.site/2016/02/some-usefull-commands-in-docker/</guid><description>I started playing with Docker and here I will write some commands that where not so obvious at beginning 😃
List running containers:
docker ps List also not running containers:
docker ps -a Remove all containers (be careful with that):
docker rm $(docker ps -a -q) Remove all images:
docker rmi $(docker images -q) Docker won&amp;rsquo;t remove any old volumes used by containers, so after some time you may be interested in deleting them all:</description></item></channel></rss>