<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bash on Tom&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://gagor.pro/tags/bash/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bash on Tom&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Content licensed under &lt;a rel=&#34;license noopener noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;(CC BY-SA 4.0)&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://gagor.pro/tags/bash/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Automatic updates of Docker images with Renovate Bot</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2024/03/automatic-updates-of-docker-images-with-renovate-bot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2024/03/automatic-updates-of-docker-images-with-renovate-bot/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing recently about best practices for patching and deprecating Docker images , but today I want to show how to automate a huge part of this process.
You might already hear about Dependabot1, it&amp;rsquo;s a Github&amp;rsquo;s way to notify developers about security vulnerabilities in their projects. Renovate2 is similar tool3, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t require Github. For my professional work I use Bitbucket, so Renovate feels more universal as can be used anywhere.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I stopped worrying and loved the GNU Make and Makefiles</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2024/02/how-i-stopped-worrying-and-loved-the-gnu-make-and-makefiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2024/02/how-i-stopped-worrying-and-loved-the-gnu-make-and-makefiles/</guid>
      <description>First contact with make When I was invited for my first job interview in the IT, I&amp;rsquo;ve been asked such question:
How would you typically build a program from sources, what commands will you use?
I answered:
It&amp;rsquo;s obvious:
./configure make make install Those times belong to the past now and not many programmers use GNU Make1 nowadays. Try asking this question and you will see disgust at best.
For many it&amp;rsquo;s the fist contact with make and often the last one, but not for me &amp;#x1f609;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My pre-commit config for Hugo blog</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2024/01/my-pre-commit-config-for-hugo-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2024/01/my-pre-commit-config-for-hugo-blog/</guid>
      <description>I love blogging with Hugo&amp;thinsp; external link and I have two blogs already that use it. The good thing about static sites is that you have all the data in the files. You can optimize them locally, batch process, amend, etc. Powerful templating engine allows to quickly pre fill documents in the format I like.
I have some steps in the Makefile for things like image optimization, but I often don&amp;rsquo;t remember to run them &amp;#x1f603;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Git hacks - a set of my favorite git aliases</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2024/01/git-hacks-a-set-of-my-favorite-git-aliases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2024/01/git-hacks-a-set-of-my-favorite-git-aliases/</guid>
      <description>I use Git a lot, even writing this article i will commit text few times. There&amp;rsquo;s a set of aliases I rely on daily and they&amp;rsquo;re first I add in new place.
Some Git commands are unnecessarily verbose. You can make your life much easier with bash-completions, but if you write it tens of times per day, it&amp;rsquo;s anyway a lot of typing&amp;hellip; and I&amp;rsquo;m a lazy man &amp;#x1f604;
Simple status/log checks git s s = status --short --branch --untracked-files Shows a short, branch-focused status with untracked files.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The best way to get NVM working in CI/CD systems</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2023/04/the-best-way-to-get-nvm-working-in-ci/cd-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2023/04/the-best-way-to-get-nvm-working-in-ci/cd-systems/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR While reasoning is important, readers may not be interested in all the frustrations I experienced while figuring out how to get things done. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a quick solution, skip to the &amp;ldquo;What eventually worked?&amp;rdquo; section. However, if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the thought process behind the solution, keep reading.
Why? Some might bother why the hell I&amp;rsquo;d like to make my life so hard? &amp;#x1f923;
We used to use nodeenv&amp;thinsp; external link for that purpose.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatically add ticket ID to every commit message in Git</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2021/11/automatically-add-ticket-id-to-every-commit-message-in-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2021/11/automatically-add-ticket-id-to-every-commit-message-in-git/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t know how it is in your company, but in mine it&amp;rsquo;s considered a good practice to add ticket numbers to commit messages. It allows to easily determine why something was changed, etc. Makes sense, but this also means, that I should be adding this ticket to every message&amp;hellip; And this doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense for me. I will accidentally avoid it from time to time or make a lot of typos.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resize images from command line on MacOS</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2021/11/resize-images-from-command-line-on-macos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2021/11/resize-images-from-command-line-on-macos/</guid>
      <description>I was updating my blog and needed to generate few variants of images, in different resolution.
Option 1 - sips There&amp;rsquo;s simple, builtin tool sips, that can be used for simple resizing 1:
Resize single image sips -Z 36 orig.png --out static/favicon36x36.png -Z - maintain image aspect ratio 36 - maximum height and width It can be also used for batch image processing:
Warning
Beware, without &amp;ndash;out param, it will overwrite images in place!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homebrew - uninstall formula with dependencies</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2021/11/homebrew-uninstall-formula-with-dependencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2021/11/homebrew-uninstall-formula-with-dependencies/</guid>
      <description>I use brew extensively on MacOS. It&amp;rsquo;s just as convenient as many Linux package managers. What I don&amp;rsquo;t like, it leaves dependencies after removal of formula. There&amp;rsquo;s simple way to clean it up by running one command 1.
Uninstall with dependencies brew uninstall FORMULA brew autoremove Info
In my case running brew autoremove actually removed few packages I really wanted to have. Check the output carefully!
https://stackoverflow.com/questions/7323261/uninstall-remove-a-homebrew-package-including-all-its-dependencies&amp;thinsp; external link &amp;#160;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to remove geo-localization/EXIF data from photos</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2021/03/how-to-remove-geo-localization/exif-data-from-photos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2021/03/how-to-remove-geo-localization/exif-data-from-photos/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to share publicly some photos, but I performed them with navigation enabled so they contained accurate localization of my house. I wanted to remove EXIF data GPS tags, my phone type and other irrelevant stuff.
Tip
There&amp;rsquo;s a way that requires less effort. Check how to automate this process with pre-commit hooks&amp;thinsp; external link .
TL;DR You will need imagemagick installed (use apt/yum/dnf of whatever you have there):</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving from Linux to MacOS – first steps</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2020/01/moving-from-linux-to-macos-first-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2020/01/moving-from-linux-to-macos-first-steps/</guid>
      <description>Few years ago I moved from Linux desktop to MacOS for my business, day to day work. There were 2 main reasons for that:
Corporations don&amp;rsquo;t like Linux - they can&amp;rsquo;t manage it, they can&amp;rsquo;t support it, so they blocked it with &amp;ldquo;Security policy&amp;rdquo;, ISO20001, or other nonsense. Actually they&amp;rsquo;re partially right but in different place - many business collaboration applications don&amp;rsquo;t work well on LInux (or they don&amp;rsquo;t work at all) Skype for Business - there&amp;rsquo;s open source alternative but to get full support you have to pay for additional codecs (as far as I remember) - it&amp;rsquo;s not working stable even in paid version Outlook and calendar support - I love Thunderbird and I use it for years, but calendar invitations didn&amp;rsquo;t work nice (honestly, they didn&amp;rsquo;t work nice even between different Outlook versions&amp;hellip;) Corporate VPN apps - Christ, I always was able to get it working eventually, but&amp;hellip; why bother I&amp;rsquo;m older, maybe lazier, maybe smarter - I don&amp;rsquo;t like to spend my time resolving problems that don&amp;rsquo;t give me any value.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to stole ssh session when you’re root</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2016/04/how-to-stole-ssh-session-when-youre-root/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2016/04/how-to-stole-ssh-session-when-youre-root/</guid>
      <description>It happen to me all the time that one of developers notifies me about some kind of problem that I can&amp;rsquo;t confirm from my account. Sometimes it was because of bad ssh keys configuration, other times file permissions, mostly such stuff. It&amp;rsquo;s sometimes convenient to &amp;ldquo;enter into someone&amp;rsquo;s shoes&amp;rdquo; to see what&amp;rsquo;s going on there.
If you&amp;rsquo;re root on machine you may do that like this:
su developer - Easy one but that&amp;rsquo;s not enough for all cases.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>pip - uninstall package with dependencies</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2016/04/pip-uninstall-package-with-dependencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2016/04/pip-uninstall-package-with-dependencies/</guid>
      <description>Virtualenvs in python are cheap but from time to time you will install something with pip on your system and when time comes removing all this crap could be difficult. I found this bash snippet that will uninstall package with all dependencies:
for dep in $(pip show python-neutronclient | grep Requires | sed &amp;#39;s/Requires: //g; s/,//g&amp;#39;) ; do sudo pip uninstall -y $dep ; done pip uninstall -y python-neutronclient Source: http://stackoverflow.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use bastion host with Ansible</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2016/04/use-bastion-host-with-ansible/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2016/04/use-bastion-host-with-ansible/</guid>
      <description>When you deploy your application in cloud you don&amp;rsquo;t need and don&amp;rsquo;t want your hosts exposed via SSH to the world. Malware scans whole network for easy SSH access and when find something will try some brute force attacks, overloading such machines. It&amp;rsquo;s easier to have one exposed, but secured host, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t host anything and is used as proxy/gateway to access our infrastructure- it&amp;rsquo;s called bastion host&amp;thinsp; external link .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>List octal file permissions in bash</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2016/02/list-octal-file-permissions-in-bash/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2016/02/list-octal-file-permissions-in-bash/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s easier to use octal file permissions but they&amp;rsquo;re not so easy to list. I caught myself few times that I didn&amp;rsquo;t remember how to list them - so this is a reason for that note.
stat -c &amp;#34;%a %n&amp;#34; * 755 bin 755 games 755 include Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s that easy &amp;#x1f603;
And here also with human readable attributes:
stat -c &amp;#39;%A %a %n&amp;#39; * drwxr-xr-x 755 bin drwxr-xr-x 755 games drwxr-xr-x 755 include </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatically build after file change</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2016/02/automatically-build-after-file-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2016/02/automatically-build-after-file-change/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m playing a lot with Docker lately. Building images, and then rebuilding, and then building again&amp;hellip; It&amp;rsquo;s pretty boring. To automate this task a little I used inotify to build automatically after I changed any file. This trick could be used in many different situations.
You will need inotify-tools package:
sudo apt-get install -y inotify-tools Then run something like this:
while inotifywait -e modify -r .; do docker-compose build; done This commands will rebuild my Docker images after any file change in current directory.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Install WordPress from command-line</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2016/02/install-wordpress-from-command-line/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2016/02/install-wordpress-from-command-line/</guid>
      <description>I never tried it before but today I needed to install WordPress&amp;hellip; From command line only. And there is a way to do this with wp-cli&amp;thinsp; external link .
WP-CLI installation First some requirements (as root):
apt-get install php5-cli php5-mysql mysql-client curl And now installation of wp-cli (as root too):
curl -O https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wp-cli/builds/gh-pages/phar/wp-cli.phar chmod +x wp-cli.phar mv wp-cli.phar /usr/local/bin/wp Check if it&amp;rsquo;s working:
$ wp --version WP-CLI 0.22.0 WordPress installation Now you should switch to user of your web application, ex.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nagios - downtime on host/service from command line with curl</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2016/01/nagios-downtime-on-hostservice-from-command-line-with-curl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2016/01/nagios-downtime-on-hostservice-from-command-line-with-curl/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes deployment process or other havy task may cause some Nagios checks to rise below normal levels and bother admin. If this is expected and you want to add downtime on host/service during this task you may use this script:
#!/bin/bash function die { echo $1; exit 1; } if [[ $# -eq 0 ]] ; then die &amp;#34;Give hostname and time in minutes as parameter!&amp;#34; fi if [[ $# -eq 1 ]] ; then MINUTES=15 else MINUTES=$2 fi HOST=$1 NAGURL=http://nagios.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Changing default php.ini file for PHP-CLI on CentOS</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2014/05/changing-default-php-ini-file-for-php-cli-on-centos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2014/05/changing-default-php-ini-file-for-php-cli-on-centos/</guid>
      <description>On Debian in default installation you have different configuration files for PHP in Apache, FPM, CLI, etc. But on CentOS you have only one php.ini for all of them. In case I have, I need to have different configuration file for scripts running in CLI mode (more memory, etc). I could run it like this:
php -c /etc/php-cli.ini script.php But this a little burdensome. So I do it like this:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Command to change root password</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2014/05/command-to-change-root-password/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2014/05/command-to-change-root-password/</guid>
      <description>Everybody knows passwd command but it&amp;rsquo;s useless when you need to change ex. root password from command line without waiting for input. In such case oneliner below could help:
echo &amp;#34;root:new_password&amp;#34; | chpasswd </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing two lists in bash</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2014/02/comparing-two-lists-in-bash/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2014/02/comparing-two-lists-in-bash/</guid>
      <description>I had quite simple task - compare two lists of hosts and check if hosts from first one are also on the second one. I started with diff:
diff -u biglist.txt hosts_to_check.txt | grep -E &amp;#34;^\+&amp;#34; It was fine but output needs some filtering to get what I want.
I&amp;rsquo;ve found another example with grep:
grep -Fxv -f biglist.txt hosts_to_check.txt | sort -n This will search for all lines in hosts_to_check.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regenerate thumbnails in Shotwell 0.15 (for last month)</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2014/01/regenerate-thumbnails-in-shotwell-for-last-month/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2014/01/regenerate-thumbnails-in-shotwell-for-last-month/</guid>
      <description>I love Shotwell&amp;thinsp; external link for it&amp;rsquo;s simplicity and easy export to Piwigo&amp;thinsp; external link . After Christmas I added new photos to my library but after that I made some modifications to them (red eye reduction, etc&amp;hellip;). Because Shotwell generate thumbnails only on import, all my modifications were not visible on preview.
I&amp;rsquo;ve started searching how to regenerate thumbs and found this info&amp;thinsp; external link . There were two issues with this method:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Debian - zablokowanie aktualizacji pakietu</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2013/11/debian-zablokowanie-aktualizacji-pakietu/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2013/11/debian-zablokowanie-aktualizacji-pakietu/</guid>
      <description>W teorii nie powinno się blokować aktualizacji pakietów bo łatają dziury itd&amp;hellip;. Ale! Zdarzyły mi się ostatnio dwie sytuacje, które do tego mnie zmusiły:
aktualizacja hudsona kończyła się błędem przy starcie usługi, aktualizacja domU Xen skończyła się problemem z kompatybilnością mechanizmu udev w systemie i jądrze (hypervisor miał starsze jądro niż spodziewało się DomU). W takich sytuacjach bardzo przydaje się możliwość zablokowania aktualizacji jednej &amp;ldquo;psującej&amp;rdquo; paczki na pewien okres czasu by nie opóźniać innych aktualizacji a sobie dać czas na rozpracowanie problemu.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kopiowanie wolumenów LVM z dd i netcat</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2013/09/kopiowanie-wolumenow-lvm-z-dd-i-netcat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2013/09/kopiowanie-wolumenow-lvm-z-dd-i-netcat/</guid>
      <description>Niedawno chciałem skopiować maszynę wirtualną z jednego hypervisora na innego. Były to 3 wolumeny LVM o rozmiarach od 50 do 100GB. Dawno temu zrobiłem sobie skrypty do backupu - jeden kompresuje wolumeny LVM - a drugi pozwala odtworzyć z dekompresja na drugim serwerze. Tyle że przy tak dużej maszynce będzie to trwało masakrycznie długo - fajnie byłoby móc równocześnie kopiować i odtwarzać (live)&amp;hellip;
I wtedy przypomniało mi się narzędzie netcat - zrobiłem snapshoty wolumenów i mogłem zaczynać.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tworzenie patch’y z poleceniami diff i patch</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2013/04/tworzenie-patchy-z-poleceniami-diff-i-patch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2013/04/tworzenie-patchy-z-poleceniami-diff-i-patch/</guid>
      <description>Jest kilka powodów dla których tworzenie patchy jest przydatne - jeśli tu jesteś to pewnie masz jakiś własny&amp;hellip;
Tworzenie patch&amp;rsquo;a diff -crB old new &amp;gt; from-old-to-new.patch W powyższym poleceniu założyłem że old i new to katalogi z wieloma podkatalogami i plikami - stąd opcja -r. -c dodaje kilka linijek &amp;ldquo;kontekstu&amp;rdquo; przez co łatwiej rozeznać się w patch&amp;rsquo;u. Opcja -B ignoruje puste linie, których patchowanie mnie nie interesuje.
Patchowanie Na początek zawsze warto wywołać polecenie z opcją -dry-run by zobaczyć czy patch wykona się poprawnie:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rozsynchronizowane serwery NTP</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2013/03/rozsynchronizowane-serwery-ntp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2013/03/rozsynchronizowane-serwery-ntp/</guid>
      <description>Miałem ostatnio zabawną sytuację gdy kilka serwerów z zainstalowanym NTPD miało rozjazdy rzędu kilkunastu sekund. Wyszło na to że moje serwery synchronizowały się z różnymi zewnętrznymi serwerami NTP pomiędzy, którymi były rozjazdy i te rozjazdy synchronizowały się na moich serwerach. Jeden &amp;ldquo;z moich&amp;rdquo; ustanowiłem głównym a wszystkie inne przekierowałem na niego (komentując wszystkie inne serwery NTP w konfiguracji). Wymusiłem synchronizację:
ntp -q Sprawdziłem jak duży jest offset i jitter (powinny być bardzo małe):</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linux - naprawianie bad sectorów</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2012/12/linux-naprawianie-bad-sectorow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2012/12/linux-naprawianie-bad-sectorow/</guid>
      <description>Dyski się zużywają i w końcu wcześniej czy później pojawiają się na nich bad sectory. Jeden z moich dysków ciut się posypał a że służy wyłącznie do backupów to mogę z tym żyć. Ale z drugiej strony jeżeli już będę musiał sięgnąć do backupów to chcę mieć pewność że coś odzyskam, dlatego postanowiłem zrobić kilka testów. Nawet jeśli nie naprawi to sektorów to przynajmniej zostaną zaznaczone jako uszkodzone i realokowane.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nginx - kompresowanie plików dla gzip_static</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2012/12/nginx-kompresowanie-plikow-dla-gzip_static/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2012/12/nginx-kompresowanie-plikow-dla-gzip_static/</guid>
      <description>Ruski serwer WWW&amp;thinsp; external link ma przydatną funkcję serwowania wersji plików skompresowanych gzip&amp;rsquo;em - przez co możemy plik skompresować raz i będzie on serwowany klientom obsługującym kompresję HTTP ale już bez każdorazowego kompresowania go. Jest to bardzo przydatne na stronach z dużym ruchem gdzie można w ten sposób zaoszczędzić takty CPU na właściwą obsługę połączeń a nie kompresję. Drugie miejsce gdzie może to być przydatne to VPS&amp;rsquo;y i &amp;ldquo;cienkie&amp;rdquo; serwery, które na kompresji przy większym obciążeniu spędzają zbyt dużo czasu i daje się to odczuć w działaniu strony.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ldapsearch w Active Directory</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2012/12/ldapsearch-w-active-directory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2012/12/ldapsearch-w-active-directory/</guid>
      <description>Można lubieć AD, można go nie lubieć&amp;hellip; Ale jak już się ma to warto czasem zintegrować go z tym&amp;hellip; i tamtym&amp;hellip; Od strony Linuksa najwygodniej można to osiągnąć przez LDAP. A żeby to dobrze zrobić trzeba najpierw przetestować czy aby wszystko działa jak byśmy sobie tego życzyli. I tutaj bardzo przydatne jest narzędzie ldapsearch.
Do odpytywania LDAP&amp;rsquo;a potrzebujemy jeden pakiecik, który zawiera kilka narzędzi do jego obsługi:
apt-get install ldap-utils Teraz możemy próbować przeszukiwać katalog np.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LVM na RAID5 i dysku z sektorami 4KB</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2012/11/lvm-na-raid5-i-dysku-z-sektorami-4kb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2012/11/lvm-na-raid5-i-dysku-z-sektorami-4kb/</guid>
      <description>Po zakupie nowych dysków zamierzam utworzyć zdegradowaną macierz RAID5 z dwóch dysków (na trzecim na razie znajdują się dane), potem utworzyć wolumen LVM, sformatować go, przekopiować dane z pojedynczego dysku na macierz i dołączyć trzeci dysk do macierzy odbudowując parzystość. Zadanie będzie o tyle ciekawe że dysk ma 4KB sektory i trzeb będzie dbać o wyrównanie zasobu do rozmiaru sektora, a w przypadku LVM&amp;rsquo;a wyrównanie do chunk&amp;rsquo;a z macierzy.
Prawidłowe wyrównanie partycji Kupując nowy dysk (o pojemności od 500GB w górę), mamy spore szanse że trafimy na sztukę, która wykorzystuje 4KB sektory do alokacji danych.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prosty MTA z heirloom-mailx i ssmtp</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2012/11/prosty-mta-z-heirloom-mailx-i-ssmtp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2012/11/prosty-mta-z-heirloom-mailx-i-ssmtp/</guid>
      <description>Czasami potrzebny jest nam serwer pocztowy, który przyśle informacje dla root&amp;rsquo;a (np. monity smartd, mdadm, sypnięte crony itp) ale równocześnie nie chcemy stawiać pełnego serwera typu postfix/exim. Warto w tym celu wykorzystać zestaw heirloom-mailx + ssmtp. hairloom-mailx jest prostym shellowym klientem SMTP - przy okazji linkuje polecenie mail (przydatne w skryptach). ssmtp pełni funkcję serwera SMTP ale nie działa jako demon - proces uruchamia się gdy jest potrzebny i znika po wysłaniu maili.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sprawdzanie nieaktywnych linków na stronie</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2012/09/sprawdzanie-nieaktywnych-linkow-na-stronie/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2012/09/sprawdzanie-nieaktywnych-linkow-na-stronie/</guid>
      <description>Gdy administruje się dużymi stronami internetowymi raz na czas np. po większych zmianach w konfiguracji zachodzi potrzeba sprawdzenia czy na stronie nie ma stron prowadzących donikąd. O ile w małych serwisach można samemu szybko przeklikać się przez stronkę to dla starych rozrośniętych serwisów nie jest to takie proste.
Jest kilka narzędzi których można użyć do testowania linków na stronach - każde z nich ma swoje zalety i wady, postaram się je przybliżyć.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>unicode-rxvt - moje ustawienia</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2012/09/unicode-rxvt-moje-ustawienia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2012/09/unicode-rxvt-moje-ustawienia/</guid>
      <description>Wybór dobrego X-terminala to w życiu admina prawie jak wybór żony&amp;hellip; spędza się wspólnie dużo czasu i miło gdy estetycznie wygląda, robi to co chcemy, itd&amp;hellip; 😉
Nie lubię gnome-terminal&#39;a bo domyślnie binduje F10 co wnerwia mnie w midnight commanderze, stąd szukałem i szukałem i jak dotychczas najbardziej podpasował mi unicode-rxvt. Można uruchamiać go po prostu jako urxvt lub uruchomić demona urxvtd po zalogowaniu i potem odpalać tylko klienta urxvtc. Druga metoda skutkuje natychmiastowym startem terminala, wiec gdy podbinduję go sobie pod F12 mam terminal zawsze pod ręką w mniej niż sekundę.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Przeszukiwanie plików danego typu pod kątem tekstu</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2012/08/przeszukiwanie-plikow-danego-typu-pod-katem-tekstu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2012/08/przeszukiwanie-plikow-danego-typu-pod-katem-tekstu/</guid>
      <description>Kiedyś poproszono mnie o przeszukanie wszystkich plików php na serwerze webowym po kątem wywołania pewnej funkcji. Oczywiste wydało mi się użycie rekurencyjnie grep&amp;rsquo;a, więc:
grep -R &amp;#34;JAKAS_FUNKCJA&amp;#34; /var/www/*.php Ale szybko okazało się że grep dopasowuje maskę *.php również do katalogów, więc nie przeszukiwał katalogów które nie kończyły się na .php ehhh&amp;hellip;..
Drugie podejście okazało się trafniejsze - najpierw poleceniem find wyszukuję wszystkie pliki php, a dopiero później grepuję (wypisując nazwę pliku i numer linii):</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wysyłanie załączników poleceniem mail</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pro/2011/08/wysylanie-zalacznikow-poleceniem-mail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pro/2011/08/wysylanie-zalacznikow-poleceniem-mail/</guid>
      <description>Kiedyś potrzebowałem w ramach testu obciążeniowego wysłać dużo wiadomości z załącznikami. Chciałem to zrobić na szybko z shell&amp;rsquo;a i tutaj chwilę musiałem pogooglać aby znaleźć działające polecenie. To co znalazłem wygląda tak:
(echo &amp;#34;testowa wiadomosc&amp;#34;; uuencode test.zip test.zip) \ | mail -s &amp;#34;Test&amp;#34; testowy@mail.pl Wiedząc już jak wysyłać maile z załącznikami, mały mail bombing mogłem zrobić tak:
for i in `seq 1 100`; do (cat tekst.txt; uuencode test.zip test.zip) \ | mail -s &amp;#34;Test $i&amp;#34; testowy@mail.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
