<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>git on Tom&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://gagor.pl/tags/git/</link>
    <description>Recent content in git on Tom&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Content licensed under &lt;a rel=&#34;license noopener noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;(CC BY-SA 4.0)&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://gagor.pl/tags/git/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My pre-commit config for Hugo blog</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pl/2024/01/my-pre-commit-config-for-hugo-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pl/2024/01/my-pre-commit-config-for-hugo-blog/</guid>
      <description>I love blogging with Hugo and I have two blogs already that use it. The good thing about static sites is that you have all the data in the files. You can optimize them locally, batch process, amend, etc. Powerful templating engine allows to quickly pre fill documents in the format I like.
I have some steps in the Makefile for things like image optimization, but I often don&amp;rsquo;t remember to run them &amp;#x1f603;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Git hacks - a set of my favorite git aliases</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pl/2024/01/git-hacks-a-set-of-my-favorite-git-aliases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pl/2024/01/git-hacks-a-set-of-my-favorite-git-aliases/</guid>
      <description>I use Git a lot, even writing this article i will commit text few times. There&amp;rsquo;s a set of aliases I rely on daily and they&amp;rsquo;re first I add in new place.
Some Git commands are unnecessarily verbose. You can make your life much easier with bash-completions, but if you write it tens of times per day, it&amp;rsquo;s anyway a lot of typing&amp;hellip; and I&amp;rsquo;m a lazy man &amp;#x1f604;
Simple status/log checks git s s = status --short --branch --untracked-files Shows a short, branch-focused status with untracked files.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatically add ticket ID to every commit message in Git</title>
      <link>https://gagor.pl/2021/11/automatically-add-ticket-id-to-every-commit-message-in-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gagor.pl/2021/11/automatically-add-ticket-id-to-every-commit-message-in-git/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t know how it is in your company, but in mine it&amp;rsquo;s considered a good practice to add ticket numbers to commit messages. It allows to easily determine why something was changed, etc. Makes sense, but this also means, that I should be adding this ticket to every message&amp;hellip; And this doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense for me. I will accidentally avoid it from time to time or make a lot of typos.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
