<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>MacOS on timor&#39;s site</title>
    <link>https://timor.site/tags/macos/</link>
    <description>Recent content in MacOS on timor&#39;s site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Content licensed under &lt;a rel=&#34;license noopener noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;(CC BY-SA 4.0)&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://timor.site/tags/macos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Automatically add ticket ID to every commit message in Git</title>
      <link>https://timor.site/2021/11/automatically-add-ticket-id-to-every-commit-message-in-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://timor.site/2021/11/automatically-add-ticket-id-to-every-commit-message-in-git/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t know how it is in your company, but in mine it&amp;rsquo;s considered a good practice to add ticket numbers to commit messages. It allows to easily determine why something was changed, etc. Makes sense, but this also means, that I should be adding this ticket to every message&amp;hellip; And this doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense for me. I will accidentally avoid it from time to time or make a lot of typos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resize images from command line on MacOS</title>
      <link>https://timor.site/2021/11/resize-images-from-command-line-on-macos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://timor.site/2021/11/resize-images-from-command-line-on-macos/</guid>
      <description>I was updating my blog and needed to generate few variants of images, in different resolution.
Option 1 - sips There&amp;rsquo;s simple, builtin tool sips, that can be used for simple resizing 1:
Resize single image sips -Z 36 orig.png --out static/favicon36x36.png -Z - maintain image aspect ratio 36 - maximum height and width It can be also used for batch image processing:
Warning
Beware, without &amp;ndash;out param, it will overwrite images in place!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homebrew - uninstall formula with dependencies</title>
      <link>https://timor.site/2021/11/homebrew-uninstall-formula-with-dependencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://timor.site/2021/11/homebrew-uninstall-formula-with-dependencies/</guid>
      <description>I use brew extensively on MacOS. It&amp;rsquo;s just as convenient as many Linux package managers. What I don&amp;rsquo;t like, it leaves dependencies after removal of formula. There&amp;rsquo;s simple way to clean it up by running one command 1.
Uninstall with dependencies brew uninstall FORMULA brew autoremove Info
In my case running brew autoremove actually removed few packages I really wanted to have. Check the output carefully!
https://stackoverflow.com/questions/7323261/uninstall-remove-a-homebrew-package-including-all-its-dependencies&amp;#160;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving from Linux to MacOS – first steps</title>
      <link>https://timor.site/2020/01/moving-from-linux-to-macos-first-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://timor.site/2020/01/moving-from-linux-to-macos-first-steps/</guid>
      <description>Few years ago I moved from Linux desktop to MacOS for my business, day to day work. There were 2 main reasons for that:
Corporations don&amp;rsquo;t like Linux - they can&amp;rsquo;t manage it, they can&amp;rsquo;t support it, so they blocked it with &amp;ldquo;Security policy&amp;rdquo;, ISO20001, or other nonsense. Actually they&amp;rsquo;re partially right but in different place - many business collaboration applications don&amp;rsquo;t work well on LInux (or they don&amp;rsquo;t work at all) Skype for Business - there&amp;rsquo;s open source alternative but to get full support you have to pay for additional codecs (as far as I remember) - it&amp;rsquo;s not working stable even in paid version Outlook and calendar support - I love Thunderbird and I use it for years, but calendar invitations didn&amp;rsquo;t work nice (honestly, they didn&amp;rsquo;t work nice even between different Outlook versions&amp;hellip;) Corporate VPN apps - Christ, I always was able to get it working eventually, but&amp;hellip; why bother I&amp;rsquo;m older, maybe lazier, maybe smarter - I don&amp;rsquo;t like to spend my time resolving problems that don&amp;rsquo;t give me any value.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
